Business and Economics College Records 1951-1976
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Business and Economics College Records
1951-1976
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Archives 43
approximate 6400 items 7.5 linear feet 8 containers
Includes material received by Dean Eugene Clark relative to meetings, programs, and staffing procedures within the college during his twenty year tenure as Dean.
Organizational History:
Courses in economics have been offered at Washington State University since the school was first opened in 1892. The original Department of Economic Science and History was incorporated into the College of Sciences and Arts in 1917 and it became the Department of Business Administration in 1926. Composed of five faculty members, the department offered, in addition to the regular economics courses, a thorough program in Secretarial Science. The staff increased to fifteen in 1928 and in the same year Business Administration was elevated to the status of a "school," although it functioned within the College of Sciences and Arts until 1940 when it was given independent status. Economics continued as a separate department in the College of Sciences and Arts until the two disciplines were merged in 1948 by Dr. M. W. Lee into the School of Economics and Business. It was given college status in 1963 with Dr. Eugene Clark functioning as the first dean. More recently the name was changed to the College of Business and Economics.
The records of the College of Business and Economics are arranged into six series. The majority of the collection is material received by Dean Eugene Clark relative to meetings, programs, and staffing procedures within the college during his twenty year tenure as dean. In this capacity he also took an active role in the affairs of the Council of Academic Deans and served as a representative to the National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges. The records are principally arranged chronologically, except the general subject files which are arranged alphabetically.
Series one consists of records from Academic Deans meetings, 1957-1976, and includes two subseries: Agendas, and Memoranda and Reports. Agendas are for the period 1968 through 1976 and are arranged chronologically. Memoranda and Reports cover the period 1957 through 1976. They are arranged alphabetically by topic with the "General Memoranda" placed at the beginning of the subseries. The second series, Bureau of Economic and Business Research, 1959-1972, contains administrative records, proposals and papers of the Bureau, a subordinate agency which studied regional marketing trends in cooperation with area businesses. It is composed of two subseries: Administrative, 1959-1972, and Proposals and Papers, 1962, 1966, 1969-1973. The records concerning the Department of Business Administration, 1958-1976, constitute the third series which are divided into two subseries: Administrative, 1966-1975, and Committees and Curriculum, 1957-1976. The Administrative subseries consists of general memoranda and minutes of faculty meetings, while Committees and Curriculum subseries includes files of departmental committees and curriculum information. Series four, Department of Economics, 1953-1976, is arranged in a similar manner. Series five, Other Departmental Programs, 1954-1976, is arranged into four subseries: Graduate School, 1962, 1967-1976; Honors Program, 1953-1972; Summer School, 1962-1973; and Administrative and Secretarial Studies, 1955-1972. The final series, General Subject files, 1951-1977, is arranged alphabetically by subject and includes the department budget reports from 1958 to 1969 and the records relating to various university committees and programs. A significant number of files in this series relate to the Computer Instructional Program and the 1966 Vocational Education Act.
The Collection is open for research use.
The records of the College of Business and Economics were transferred to the Washington State University Libraries in August 1977 (UA 77-24) and in January 1979 (UA 79-2) in accordance with the approved records schedule.
Clark, Eugene, 1917---Archives
Washington State University. College of Business & Economics--Archives; State College of Washington. Dept. of Business Administration.; Washington State University. School of Economics and Business.; Washington State University. College of Business & Economics--Records and correspondence; Washington State University. College of Business & Economics--Curricula--History
Business schools--Washington (State)--Archives
College administrators--Washington (State)--Archives
Washington (State); Colleges and Universities
- Academic Deans Meeting, 1957-1976; 1
  - Agendas, 1968-1976
    - 1968-December 1976, 640 items (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
  - Memoranda and Reports, 1957-1976
    - General Memoranda, 1957-1968; 105 items (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Budget Subcommittee, 1976; 30 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Continuing Education Report, 1975; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Departmental Development Plans, 1975; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Mitchell Report, 1971; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Performance Audit, 1975; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Review of Performance, 1976; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Retreat, 1976; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Bureau of Economic and Business Research, 1959-1972; 2
  - Administrative, 1959-1972
    - General Correspondence, 1959-1965; 40 items (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Memoranda, 1966-1975; 30 items (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Cooperation with CBD, Univ. of Idaho, 1972; 10 items (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Editorials, 1963; 3 items (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Planned Projects, 1963-1964; 7 items (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Proceedures, 1962-1966; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Summer:
      - Program, 1970; 15 items (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Research Applications, 1969; 30 items (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Proposals and Papers, 1962, 1966, 1969-1973
    - Guthrie and Iulo Report, 2 items (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Iulo and Cook Reports, 1971; 8 items (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Leigh Report, 1973; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Rawlins Report, 1973; 34 items (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Recreation Research Center, 1966; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Savings League Research, 1972; 5 items (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Statement of Principles, 1962; 5 items (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Travel, Tourism, and Recreation Report, 1972; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Department of Business Administration, 1957-1976; 3
  - Administrative, 1966-1975
    - General Memoranda, July 1966-June 1975; 225 items (Box 2, Folder 39-45)
    - Faculty Meetings, 1968-1976; 205 items (Box 2, Folder 46-50)
  - Committees and Curriculum, 1957-1976
    - Advisory Distribution, 1965; 7 items (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Area Chairman, Materials, 1969; 5 items (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Attorneys, 1971; 3 items (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Brochures, n.d.; 70 items (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - CPA Information, 1962; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Committee on:
      - Department Reorganization, 1969-1975; 15 items (Box 2, Folder 56)
      - Effective Teaching, 1970; 5 items (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - Fellowships and Grants, 1970; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Communications Management and Insurance, 1964-1965; 6 items (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Curriculum:
      - 1957-1964, 30 items (Box 2, Folder 60)
      - Revision, 1960-1961; 25 items (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Developmental Program, 1969; 6 items (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Doctoral Program, 1962-1966; 15 items (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Catalog Material, 1964; 10 items (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Enrollment Procedures, 1975-1976; 15 items (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - General Policies and Procedures, 1958-1967; 65 items (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Long Range Plans, 1962; 10 items (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Off-Campus MBA Program, 1972; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Planning Policies, 1975-1976; 45 items (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Proposals:
      - Esso Grant, 1971; 5 items (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - IBM Corporation, 1971; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 71)
      - Improving Community Organization, 1971; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 72)
      - Washington Bankers Association, 1971; 75 items (Box 2, Folder 73)
- Department of Economics, 1953-1975; 4
  - Administrative, 1957-1973
    - General Information, 1971-1973; 110 items (Box 3, Folder 74-75)
    - General Memoranda, 1957-1971; 555 items (Box 3, Folder 76-82)
    - Economic Faculty Meetings, 1964, 1969-1976; 605 items (Box 3, Folder 83-93)
  - Committees and Curriculum:
    - Chairman:
      - Ballots and Reports, 1970; 45 items (Box 3, Folder 94)
      - Candidates, 1969-1970; 15 items (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Committee to Appraise Program, 1960; 10 items (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Course Offerings and Programs, 1955-1961; 50 items (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Department Reorganization, 1969; 50 items (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Foreign Language Requirement, 1965-1969; 12 items (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Geography Courses, 1953-1969; 50 items (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Graduate:
      - Student Information, 1966-1973; 225 items (Box 4, Folder 101-106)
      - Program Review, 1975-1976; 35 items (Box 4, Folder 107)
      - Student Changes, 1962-1970; 40 items (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Iulo Trip (Research Grants), 1966; 9 items (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Majors in Economics, n.d.; 5 items (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - NDEA Applications, 1959; 10 items (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Search Committee for Chairman, 1970; 70 items (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Selection Committee, 1974-1975; 45 items (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - TA's Criteria for Reappointment, 1970; 5 items (Box 4, Folder 114)
- Other Departmental Programs, 1954-1976; 5
  - Graduate School, 1962, 1967-1976
    - General Correspondence, 1967-1972; 80 items (Box 4, Folder 115-116)
    - Accreditation Discussions, 1962; 8 items (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Grants-in-Aid, 1976; 5 items (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Lubov Proposal, 1976; 3 items (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Allen Report, 1975; 2 items (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Master of Regional Planning Proposal, 1975; 2 items (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - Hammer Report, 1974; 5 items (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Hockstra Report, 1974; 1 item (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - NSF Proposals, 1974; 10 items (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Giestauts Report, 1973; 1 item (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Social and Health Services Proposals, 1972; 15 items (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - Federal Grants, 1970; 10 items (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Manpower Research Institute Grants, 1969; 5 items (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Honors Program, 1953-1972
    - Convocation, 1953-1969; 130 items (Box 4, Folder 129-130)
    - Center, 1954-1972; 240 items (Box 5, Folder 131-133)
  - Summer School, 1962-1973
    - Schedules, 1962-1966; 50 items (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - 1966-1973, 265 items (Box 5, Folder 135-142)
  - Administrative and Secretarial Studies, 1955-1972
    - Hospital Administration, 1960-1965; 45 items (Box 5, Folder 143-144)
    - Hotel Administration, 1963-1972; 35 items (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Office Administration:
      - 1955-1968, 35 items (Box 5, Folder 146)
      - Graduate Program, 1964; 20 items (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Secretarial Studies:
      - 1958-1959, 50 items (Box 5, Folder 148)
      - Catalogue Material, 1964; 20 items (Box 5, Folder 149)
- General Subject Files, 1951-1977; 6
  - Accounting Meetings, 1967; 10 items (Box 5, Folder 150)
  - Accreditation Study:
    - Accounting, 1953-1963; 12 items (Box 5, Folder 151)
    - Geography, 1969; 12 items (Box 5, Folder 152)
  - Admission Requests, n.d.; 6 items (Box 5, Folder 153)
  - Advertising Group, 1960; 3 items (Box 5, Folder 154)
  - Advisory Groups, n.d.; 1 item (Box 5, Folder 155)
  - Affirmative Action Director Search, 1973; 10 items (Box 5, Folder 156)
  - Agricultural Economics (Dr. Working), 1955-1964; 14 items (Box 5, Folder 157)
  - Agricultural Marketing Studies, 1959-1960; 20 items (Box 5, Folder 158)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1956-1977; 20 items (Box 5, Folder 159)
  - Budget Director Applications, 1974; 8 items (Box 5, Folder 160)
  - Department Budgets, 1958-1960, 1963-1969; 95 items (Box 5, Folder 161-165)
  - Business Opportunities, n.d.; 1 item (Box 5, Folder 166)
  - Campus Disorder, 1969-1970; 10 items (Box 5, Folder 167)
  - Carnegie Survey Results, 1957-1965; 7 items (Box 5, Folder 168)
  - Commercial Car Journal Controversy, 1968-1969; 6 items (Box 5, Folder 169)
  - Committees:
    - Airport, 1963; 14 items (Box 5, Folder 170)
    - Civil Rights and Educational Policy, 1962-1964; 30 items (Box 5, Folder 171)
    - Faculty-Student Conciliation, 1970; 26 items (Box 6, Folder 172)
    - Railroad Relocation, 1966; 12 items (Box 6, Folder 173)
    - Golf Course, 1966; 12 items (Box 6, Folder 174)
  - Computer Instructional Program, 1965-1973; 110 items (Box 6, Folder 175-177)
  - Council on Higher Education, 1970-1973; 110 items (Box 6, Folder 178)
  - Dean Search, 1973; 25 items (Box 6, Folder 179)
  - Directory Lists, 1965-1975; 45 items (Box 6, Folder 180)
  - Distinguished Alumnus Award, 1974; 45 items (Box 6, Folder 181)
  - Educational Professions Development Act, 1968-1969; 4 items (Box 6, Folder 182)
  - Expo '74, 1973-1974; 15 items (Box 6, Folder 183)
  - Export Expansion Council, 1966-1969; 45 items (Box 6, Folder 184)
  - Faculty Load Studies, 1962-1963; 4 items (Box 6, Folder 185)
  - Higher Education Act, 1965; 10 items (Box 6, Folder 186)
  - History of the College of Business and Education, 1942; 8 items (Box 6, Folder 187)
  - Honors and Awards, 1970-1973; 42 items (Box 6, Folder 188-190)
  - Indian Community Action Program, 1965-1967; 16 items (Box 6, Folder 191)
  - IBM Symposium, 1969; 10 items (Box 6, Folder 192)
  - Innovative Proposals, 1971-1974; 40 items (Box 6, Folder 193)
  - Institute of Technology (WSU):
    - 1958, 20 items (Box 6, Folder 194)
    - Reports, n.d.; 8 items (Box 6, Folder 195)
  - Inter-Institutional Conferences, 1970; 20 items (Box 6, Folder 196)
  - Idaho (Univ. of) Business School, 1970; 10 items (Box 6, Folder 197)
  - Land Grant School Meetings, 1963-1967; 110 items (Box 7, Folder 198-199)
  - Library Questionnaire, 1969; 25 items (Box 7, Folder 200)
  - Marketing Research Papers, 1959; 5 items (Box 7, Folder 201)
  - MBA:
    - Degrees Awarded, 1958; 8 items (Box 7, Folder 202)
    - Richland Program, 1969; 5 items (Box 7, Folder 203)
  - Mathematics, 1961-1962; 4 items (Box 7, Folder 204)
  - Mineral Resources Institute, 1973; 6 items (Box 7, Folder 205)
  - Minority Project, 1971; 8 items (Box 7, Folder 206)
  - NSF:
    - Program Drafts, 1965-1972; 12 items (Box 7, Folder 207)
    - Seminar Development Program, 1964-1965; 36 items (Box 7, Folder 208)
  - Northwest Regional Workshop, 1972; 14 items (Box 7, Folder 209)
  - Presidential Inauguration (Terrell), 1968; 10 items (Box 7, Folder 210)
  - President's Office, 1966; 50 items (Box 7, Folder 211)
  - Publicity and Print Shop, 1957-1961; 6 items (Box 7, Folder 212)
  - Racism Workshop, 1970-1971; 12 items (Box 7, Folder 213)
  - Real Estate, 1960; 4 items (Box 7, Folder 214)
  - ROTC Trip, 1967; 20 items (Box 7, Folder 215)
  - School of Education, 1964; 6 items (Box 7, Folder 216)
  - Spokane MBA Proposal, 1966-1967; 25 items (Box 7, Folder 217)
  - Staff:
    - Personnel, 1966-1973; 42 items (Box 7, Folder 218)
    - Recruitment, 1970-1971; 35 items (Box 7, Folder 219)
  - Standards for the Department, 1970-1972; 27 items (Box 7, Folder 220)
  - Student Survey, 1958; 2 items (Box 7, Folder 221)
  - University:
    - Architect, 1966-1973; 36 items (Box 7, Folder 222)
    - Regulations, 1951-1956; 13 items (Box 7, Folder 223)
    - Services, 1957-1960; 15 items (Box 7, Folder 224)
  - Veterinary Medicine Dean, 1973; 7 items (Box 7, Folder 225)
  - Vice-President:
    - General, 1966; 50 items (Box 8, Folder 226)
    - Smith, 1969; 30 items (Box 8, Folder 227)
    - Wood, 1969; 15 items (Box 8, Folder 228)
  - Visiting Professors, 1966-1972; 135 items (Box 8, Folder 229-233)
  - Vocational Education Act, 1965-1968; 50 items (Box 8, Folder 234-237)
  - Water Research Center, 1962-1963; 35 items (Box 8, Folder 238)
  - Yakima Survey, 1959; 2 items (Box 8, Folder 239)